We lost a lot of time at school learning spelling.
لقد أضعنا الكثير من الوقت في المدرسة في تعلم قواعد الإملاء.
Kids are still losing a lot of time at school with spelling.
والأطفال مازالوا يضيعون الكثير من الوقت في المدرسة في تعلم الإملاء.
That's why I want to share a question with you:
لهذا السبب أريد أن أشارككم هذا السؤال:
Do we need new spelling rules?
هل نحتاج لقواعد إملاء جديدة؟
I believe that yes, we do.
أعتقد نعم، نحتاج لذلك.
Or even better, I think we need to simplify the ones we already have.
والأفضل من ذلك، أعتقد أننا نحتاج إلى تبسيط ما بين أيدينا.
Neither the question nor the answer are new in the Spanish language.
هذا السؤال وإجابته ليس بجديد في اللغة الإسبانية.
They have been bouncing around from century to century
وتم تداوله من قرن لآخر
since 1492, when in the first grammar guide of the Spanish language,
فمنذ 1492، في الدليل النحوي الأول للغة الإسبانية،
Antonio de Nebrija, set a clear and simple principle for our spelling:
وضع أنطونيو دي نيبريا مبدأَ واضحاً وبسيطاً لعملية الهجاء:
"... thus, we have to write words as we pronounce them,
"... علينا أن نكتب الكلمات كما ننطقها،
and pronounce words as we write them."
وننطقها كما نكتبها."
Each sound was to correspond to one letter,
كل صوت يوازيه حرف واحد،
each letter was to represent a single sound,
كل حرف يمثل صوتًا فرديًا،
and those which did not represent any sound should be removed.
والحروف التي لا تمثل أي صوت يجب إزالتها.
This approach, the phonetic approach,
هذا النهج، النهج الصوتي،
which says we have to write words as we pronounce them,
والذي يحدد أن نكتب الكلمات كما ننطقها،
both is and isn't at the root of spelling as we practice it today.
وكلاهما موجود وغير موجود في الإملاء التي نمارسها اليوم.
It is, because the Spanish language, in contrast to English, French or others,
وهذا سببه أن اللغة الإسبانية على نقيض الإنجليزية والفرنسية وغيرهما،
always strongly resisted writing words too differently
قاومت دائما وبشدة أن تكتب الكلمات مغايرة
to how we pronounce them.
لطريقة نطقها.
But the phonetic approach is also absent today,
ولكن النهج الصوتي غائب أيضاً اليوم.
because when, in the 18th century, we decided how we would standardize
لأننا في القرن الثامن عشر، قررنا كيف سنوحد
our writing,
كتابتنا،
there was another approach which guided a good part of the decisions.
كان هناك توجه آخر الذي قيد جزء كبير من القرارات.
It was the etymological approach,
إنه نهج أصول الكلمات،
the one that says we have to write words
الذي يقول أنه يجب أن نكتب الكلمات
according to how they were written in their original language,
لكيفية كتابتها في لغتها الأصلية،
in Latin, in Greek.
باللاتينية أو بالإغريقية.
That's how we ended up with silent H's, which we write but don't pronounce.
وهكذا انتهينا بالحرف الصامت H الذي نكتبه ولكن لا ننطقه.
That's how we have B's and V's that, contrary to what many people believe,
ولهذا ظهرت لدينا الحروف B و V التي، خلافا لما يعتقده كثير من الناس،
were never differentiated in Spanish pronunciation.
لم تكن مختلفة أبداً في النطق الإسباني.
That's how we wound up with G's,
هذه هي الطريقة التي أوصلتنا إلى أنواع G،
that are sometimes aspirated, as in "gente,"
الذي يلفظ في بعض الأحيان ساكناً بأخذ نفس كما في "gente"،
and other times unaspirated, as in "gato."
وأحياناً آخرى لا تلفظ بنفس كما في "gato".
That's how we ended up with C's, S's and Z's,
هكذا انتهينا بـ C وS وZ،
three letters that in some places correspond to one sound,
وهي ثلاث حروف تنطق في بعض المواقع كصوت واحد،
and in others, to two, but nowhere to three.
وفي أخرى كصوتين، لكن أبدا ليس كثلاث أصوات منفصلة.
I'm not here to tell you anything you don't know from your own experience.
لست هنا لأخبركم بأمور لم تعرفوها من تجاربكم الشخصية.
We all went to school,
ذهبنا كلنا للمدرسة،
we all invested big amounts of learning time,
وكلنا بذل الكثير من وقته في التعلم،
big amounts of pliant, childlike brain time
الكثير من الوقت من طفولتنا
in dictation,
في تعلم الإملاء،
in the memorization of spelling rules filled, nevertheless, with exceptions.
في حفظ قواعد الإملاء والهجاء المليئة برغم ذلك بالاستثناءات.
We were told in many ways, implicitly and explicitly,
أخبرونا بطرق عدة، ضمناً وصراحةً
that in spelling, something fundamental to our upbringing was at stake.
أنه في الإملاء، شيء أساسي في تنشئتنا على المحك.
Yet, I have the feeling
وبرغم ذلك، أشعر
that teachers didn't ask themselves why it was so important.
أن المدرسين لم يسألوا أنفسهم عن سبب أهمية ذلك.
In fact, they didn't ask themselves a previous question:
وفي الحقيقة، لم يسألوا أنفسهم السؤال الأهم الذي يسبقه:
What is the purpose of spelling?
ما هو هدف الإملاء؟
What do we need spelling for?
لماذا نحتاج إلى قواعد الإملاء؟
And the truth is, when someone asks themselves this question,
وفي الحقيقة، عندما يسأل شخص نفسه هذا السؤال،
the answer is much simpler and less momentous
تكون الإجابة أسهل وأقل خطورة
than we'd usually believe.
مما نظن عادة.
We use spelling to unify the way we write, so we can all write the same way,
نستخدم قواعد للإملاء لنوحد طريقة كتابتنا، لكي نكتب كلنا بطريقة موحدة،
making it easier for us to understand when we read to each other.
لكي يسهل الفهم عندما نقرأ لبعضنا.
But unlike in other aspects of language such as punctuation,
لكن على عكس قواعد لغوية أخرى كقواعد علامات الترقيم،
in spelling, there's no individual expression involved.
في الإملاء لايتدخل العامل البشري.
In punctuation, there is.
بينما يتواجد في علامات الترقيم.
With punctuation, I can choose to change the meaning of a phrase.
مع علامات الترقيم، أختار بنفسي تغيير معنى الجملة.
With punctuation, I can impose a particular rhythm to what I am writing,
مع علامات الترقيم، أستطيع فرض نغم وأسلوب معين لما أكتب،
but not with spelling.
لكن لايتأتى ذلك مع الإملاء.
When it comes to spelling, it's either wrong or right,
في حال قواعد الإملاء، فتكون إما صحيحة أو خاطئة،
according to whether it conforms or not to the current rules.
وفقا لما لو كانت توافق القواعد المطروحة.
But then, wouldn't it be more sensible to simplify the current rules
لكن أليس من المنطقي أن تسهل القواعد الحالية
so it would be easier to teach, learn and use spelling correctly?
حتى يكون من الأسهل تعليم وتعلم واستخدام الإملاء بشكل صحيح؟
Wouldn't it be more sensible to simplify the current rules
ألن يكون منطقيًا أكثر تبسيط قواعد الإملاء الحالية
so that all the time we devote today to teaching spelling,
حتى نخصص الوقت الذي نبذله لتعلم الإملاء،
we could devote to other language issues
نخصصه في تعلم جوانب لغوية أخرى
whose complexities do, in fact, deserve the time and effort?
والتي تستحق جوانبها المعقدة حقيقةً وقتًا ومجهودًا أكبر؟
What I propose is not to abolish spelling,
الذي أقترحه ليس إلغاء قواعد الإملاء،
and have everyone write however they want.
ليكتب الجميع كيفما شاؤوا.
Language is a tool of common usage,
اللغة أداة للاستخدام العام،
and so I believe it's fundamental that we use it following common criteria.
لذا أعتقد أنه من الأساسي استخدامه باتباع معايير معينة.
But I also find it fundamental
لكن أجده جانباً جوهرياً
that those common criteria be as simple as possible,
أن تكون المعايير المشتركة مبسطة قدر المستطاع،
especially because if we simplify our spelling,
خاصة أنه إذا بسطنا قواعد الإملاء لدينا
we're not leveling it down;
فإننا لاندني مستواه؛
when spelling is simplified,
عند تبسيط الإملاء،
the quality of the language doesn't suffer at all.
لا تتأثر جودة اللغة إطلاقاً.
I work every day with Spanish Golden Age literature,
أنا أعمل يوميا مع الأدب الإسباني من العصر الذهبي،
I read Garcilaso, Cervantes, Góngora, Quevedo,
أنا أقرأ لجارسيلاسو، سيرفانتيس، جونجورا، كويفيدو،
who sometimes write "hombre" without H,
والذين يكتبون أحيانا "أومبري" بدون H،
sometimes write "escribir" with V,
وأحياناً يكتبون "إيسكريبير" بـ V،
and it's absolutely clear to me
والأمر واضح جداً بالنسبة لي
that the difference between those texts and ours is one of convention,
أن الفرق بين تلك النصوص وبين نصوصنا هو العرف،
or rather, a lack of convention during their time.
أو بالأصح عدم تواجد العرف في زمنهم.
But it's not a difference of quality.
ولكن الفرق ليس اختلاف في الجودة.
But let me go back to the masters,
لكن دعوني أعود للعظماء،
because they're key characters in this story.
لأنهم الشخصيات الرئيسية في هذه القصة.
Earlier, I mentioned this slightly thoughtless insistence
ذكرت مسبقاً ذلك الإصرار الذي يأتي بدون تفكير
with which teachers pester and pester us
والذي يضايقنا فيه المدرسين
over spelling.
حول قواعد الإملاء.
But the truth is, things being as they are,
لكن الحقيقة أن، إذا كانت الأمور كما هي عليه،
this makes perfect sense.
فإن الأمر يبدو منطقيًا للغاية.
In our society, spelling serves as an index of privilege,
في مجتمعنا، الإملاء بمثابة مؤشر التميز،
separating the cultured from the brute, the educated from the ignorant,
الذي يفصل المثقف من الغشيم، بين المتعلم والجاهل،
independent of the content that's being written.
بغض النظر عن المحتوى الذي يكتب.
One can get or not get a job
يستطيع المرء الحصول على وظيفة أو تضييعها
because of an H that one put or did not.
بسبب الـ H الذي كتبه أو نسيه.
One can become an object of public ridicule
قد يصبح المرء عنصر للسخرية العامة
because of a misplaced B.
بسبب B أملاها خطأً.
Therefore, in this context,
وبالتالي وفي سياق ذلك،
of course, it makes sense to dedicate all this time to spelling.
يصبح من المنطقي بذل الكثير من الوقت لتعلم الإملاء.
But we shouldn't forget
لكن علينا أن لا ننسى
that throughout the history of our language,
أنه طوال تاريخ لغتنا،
it has always been teachers
كان دوماً فيه المدرسين
or people involved in the early learning of language
أو الأشخاص المعنيين في التعليم المبكر للغة
who promoted spelling reforms,
الذين شجعوا التعديلات في قواعد الإملاء،
who realized that in our spelling there was often an obstacle
والذين أدركوا أنه طالما تواجد عائق في إملاؤنا
to the transmission of knowledge.
لنقل العلوم.
In our case, for example,
في حالتنا مثلاً،
Sarmiento, together with Andrés Bello, spearheaded the biggest spelling reform
سارمينتو، يد بيد مع أندريس بيلو، قاد أكبر عملية إصلاح للإملاء
to take place in the Spanish language:
تجري في اللغة الإسبانية:
the mid-19th century Chilean reform.
وهو الإصلاح التشيلي في منتصف القرن التاسع عشر.
Then, why not take over the task of those teachers
إذا، لماذا لا نتولى مهمة أولئك المدرسين
and start making progress in our spelling?
ونبدأ بإحراز تقدم في إملاؤنا؟
Here, in this intimate group of 10,000,
هنا، وفي هذه المجموعة الحميمة المكونة من 10ألف شخص،
I'd like to bring to the table
أود أن أحضر الطاولة لنقاش
some changes that I find reasonable to start discussing.
بعض التغييرات التي أرى منطقية البدء بمناقشتها.
Let's remove the silent H.
لنزيل حرف الـ H الصامتة.
In places where we write an H but pronounce nothing,
في المواضع التي نكتب فيها H لكن لاننطق شيئا،
let's not write anything.
لنتركه دون كتابة شيء.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It's hard for me to imagine what sentimental attachment
من الصعب علي تخيل التعلق العاطفي
can justify to someone all the hassle caused by the silent H.
الذي يبرر لشخص المتاعب المتسببة من الـ H الصامتة.
B and V, as we said before,
أما الـ B وV كما قلت مسبقاً،
were never differentiated in the Spanish language --
والتي لايتم التفريق بينها في اللغة الإسبانية --
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Let's choose one; it could be either. We can discuss it, talk it over.
لنختار أحدهما؛ من الممكن اختيار أي منهم. يمكن مناقشة ذلك والتحدث عنه.
Everyone will have their preferences and can make their arguments.
سيكون لكل منا تفضيلاته ويمكن أن يقدم حججه.
Let's keep one, remove the other.
لنحتفظ بأحدهما، ونبعد الآخر.
G and J, let's separate their roles.
أما G وJ، لنفصل أدوارهما.
G should keep the unaspirated sound, like in "gato," "mago," and "águila,"
G يحتفظ بالصوت غير الساكن، مثل "mago"، "gato" و"águila"
and J should keep the aspirated sound,
وJ يحتفظ بالصوت الساكن،
as in "jarabe," "jirafa," "gente," "argentino."
مثل "gente" "jirafa"، "jarabe" و"argentino"
The case of C, S and Z is interesting,
أما حالة C، S وZ فهي مثيرة للاهتمام،
because it shows that the phonetic approach must be a guide,
لأنه يظهر أن النهج الصوتي يجب أن يتبع،
but it can't be an absolute principle.
لكنه لايمكن أن يكون مبدأ مطلق.
In some cases, the differences in pronunciation must be addressed.
في بعض الحالات، علينا معالجة الفروق في النطق.
As I said before, C, S and Z,
كما قلت مسبقا، C، S وZ،
in some places, correspond to one sound, in others to two.
في بعض المواضع تعبر عن صوت واحد، وفي أخرى صوتين.
If we go from three letters to two, we're all better off.
إذا انتقلنا من ثلاثة أحرف إلى اثنان، سنكون بحال أفضل.
To some, these changes may seem a bit drastic.
قد تبدو هذه التغييرات للبعض قاسية جداً.
They're really not.
ليست كذلك حقاً.
The Royal Spanish Academy, all of language academies,
الأكاديمية الملكية الإسبانية، وكل أكاديميات اللغة،
also believes that spelling should be progressively modified;
يعتقدون أيضا أن الإملاء يجب تغييرها جذرياً؛
that language is linked to history, tradition and custom,
بأن اللغة مرتبطة بالتاريخ والتقاليد والعادات
but that at the same time, it is a practical everyday tool
لكنها في الوقت ذاته أداة عملية للاستخدام اليومي
and that sometimes this attachment to history, tradition and custom
وأن الربط هذا، بالتاريخ والتقاليد والعادات
becomes an obstacle for its current usage.
يصبح عائقًا لاستخداماته الحالية.
Indeed, this explains the fact
فعلا، هذا يوضح حقيقة
that our language, much more than the others we are geographically close to,
أن لغتنا، أكثر من اللغات الأخرى المتقاربة لنا جغرافياً،
has been historically modifying itself based on us,
تغيرت تاريخياً وفقاً لما حددناه نحن،
for example, we went from "ortographia" to "ortografía,"
كمثال على ذلك، نحن غيرنا من "orthographia" إلى "ortografía"،
from "theatro" to "teatro," from "quantidad" to "cantidad,"
من "theatro" إلى "teatro"، من "quantidad" إلى "cantidad"،
from "symbolo" to "símbolo."
من "symbolo" إلى "símbolo".
And some silent H's are slowly being stealthily removed:
وبعض أحرف H الصامتة يتم إزالتها بهدوء؛
in the Dictionary of the Royal Academy,
في قاموس الأكاديمية الملكية،
"arpa" and "armonía" can be written with or without an H.
"arpa" و"armonía" يمكن كتابتهم بـH أو بدونه.
And everybody is OK.
والجميع موافق.
I also believe
أنا أيضًا أعتقد
that this is a particularly appropriate moment to have this discussion.
أنه الوقت المناسب لمناقشة هذا الأمر.
It's always said that language changes spontaneously,
دائماً يقال أن اللغة تتغير بعفوية،
from the bottom up,
من أسفل الهرم لأعلاه
that its users are the ones who incorporate new words
أن مستخدميها هم من يدمجون الكلمات الجديدة
and who introduce grammatical changes,
وهم أيضا من يقدمون التغييرات النحوية،
and that the authority -- in some places an academy,
وأن السلطة -- التي تكون في بعض الأماكن هي الأكاديمية،
in others a dictionary, in others a ministry --
وفي أخرى قاموساً، وفي أخرى وزارة --
accepts and incorporates them long after the fact.
تقبل وتدمجه بعد ثباته بمدة.
This is true only for some levels of language.
وهذه حقيقة لبعض مستويات اللغة.
It is true on the lexical level, the level of words.
هي حقيقة واقعة على مستوى المفردات، على مستوى الكلمات.
It is less true on the grammatical level,
وأقل تأثيراً على مستوى قواعد النحو،
and I would almost say it is not true for the spelling level,
وأستطيع القول أنه تقريباً ليس كذلك على مستوى الإملاء،
that has historically changed from the top down.
الذي تغير على مدى التاريخ من أعلى الهرم لأسفله.
Institutions have always been the ones to establish the rules
ظلت المعاهد هي من تضع القواعد
and propose changes.
وتقترح التغييرات.
Why do I say this is a particularly appropriate moment?
لماذا أقول أنه الوقت الأنسب؟
Until today,
حتى اليوم،
writing always had a much more restricted and private use than speech.
ظلت للكتابة استخدامات خاصة ومحددة على عكس الكلام.
But in our time, the age of social networks,
لكن في وقتنا الحاضر، زمن شبكات التواصل الاجتماعي،
this is going through a revolutionary change.
وهو يمر بتغييرات ثورية.
Never before have people written so much;
لم يسبق أن كتب الناس بهذه الوفرة؛
never before have people written for so many others to see.
لم يسبق أن كتب الناس ليرى كتاباتهم الآخرون.
And in these social networks, for the first time,
وفي شبكات التواصل هذه، ولأول مرة،
we're seeing innovative uses of spelling on a large scale,
نرى استخدامات مبدعة للإملاء على مستوى ضخم،
where even more-than-educated people with impeccable spelling,
حيث حتى المتعلمين - جداً - بإملاء لايشوبه شائبة،
when using social networks,
عند استخدامهم شبكات التواصل الاجتماعي،
behave a lot like the majority of users of social networks behave.
يتصرفون كما يتصرف بقية المستخدمين لشبكات التواصل الاجتماعي.
That is to say, they slack on spell-checking
أقصد القول أنهم يتهاونون في التدقيق الإملائي
and prioritize speed and efficacy in communication.
ويجعلون الأولوية للسرعة والفعالية في التواصل.
For now, on social networks, we see chaotic, individual usages.
حتى الآن، على شبكات التواصل الاجتماعي، نرى الفوضى والاستخدامات الفردية.
But I think we have to pay attention to them,
لكن أعتقد أنه علينا أن نملي اهتماماً لهم،
because they're probably telling us
لأنهم ربما يقولون لنا
that an era that designates a new place for writing
أن عصراً حدد مكانةً جديدة للكتابة
seeks new criteria for that writing.
يبحث عن معايير جديدة للكتابة.
I think we'd be wrong to reject them, to discard them,
أعتقد أننا سنكون مخطئين لو رفضناهم أو تجاهلناهم،
because we identify them as symptoms of the cultural decay of our times.
لأننا نعرفهم كأنهم أعراض الاضمحلال الثقافي في زمننا.
No, I believe we have to observe them, organize them and channel them
لا، أعتقد أن علينا مراقبتهم بكثب، وتنظيمهم وتوجيههم
within guidelines that better correspond to the needs of our times.
ضمن مبادئ تتوافق بشكل أفضل لاحتياجات عصرنا.
I can anticipate some objections.
أستشعر بعض الاعتراضات.
There will be those who'll say
سيكون من أولئك من سيقولون
that if we simplify spelling we'll lose etymology.
أننا لو بسطنا الإملاء فسوف نفقد أصول الكلمات.
Strictly speaking, if we wanted to preserve etymology,
لنكون دقيقين في كلامنا، لو أردنا الاحتفاظ بما يمت لأصول الكلمات،
it would go beyond just spelling.
سيتجاوز مجرد الإملاء.
We'd also have to learn Latin, Greek, Arabic.
سيكون علينا أيضا تعلم اللغة اللاتينية والإغريقية والعربية.
With simplified spelling,
عند تبسيط الإملاء،
we would normalize etymology in the same place we do now:
سوف نعيد مصدر أصول الكلمات إلى المكان التي فيه الآن:
in etymological dictionaries.
في قواميس أصول الكلمات.
A second objection will come from those who say:
سيأتي اعتراض آخر ممن سيقولون:
"If we simplify spelling, we'll stop distinguishing
"لو أننا بسطنا الإملاء، لن نستطيع أن نفرق
between words that differ in just one letter."
بين الكلمات التي تختلف في حرف واحد فقط."
That is true, but it's not a problem.
هذه حقيقية، لكنها ليست مشكلة.
Our language has homonyms, words with more than one meaning,
لغتنا تحتوي الكلمات المتشابهة التي لها أكثر من معنى،
yet we don't confuse the "banco" where we sit
لكننا لانخلط الـ"banco" حيث نجلس
with the "banco" where we deposit money,
مع الـ"banco" الذي نودع فيه الأموال،
or the "traje" that we wear with the things we "trajimos."
أو الـ"traje" الذي نلبسه مع الأشياء التي "trajimos."
In the vast majority of situations, context dispels any confusion.
في أغلب الأحوال، فإن السياق هو الذي يبدد أي التباس.
But there's a third objection.
لكن هناك اعتراض ثالث.
To me,
بالنسبة لي،
it's the most understandable, even the most moving.
وهو المفهوم أكثر، والأكثر تأثيراً.
It's the people who'll say: "I don't want to change.
هو الناس الذين سيقولون: "أنا لا أريد أن أتغير
I was brought up like this, I got used to doing it this way,
نشأت كذلك، وقد اعتدت على عملها بهذه الطريقة،
when I read a written word in simplified spelling, my eyes hurt."
عندما أقرأ كلمة مكتوبة بإملاء مبسط، تؤلمني عيني."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This objection is, in part, in all of us.
هذا الاعتراض، ولو جزئياً، في داخلنا كلنا.
What do I think we should do?
ما الذي أرى أنه يجب عمله؟
The same thing that's always done in these cases:
الشيء نفسه الذي نعمله دائماً في هذه الحالات:
changes are made looking forward; children are taught the new rules,
التغييرات تعمل بالنظر قدماً؛ يلقن الأطفال القواعد الجديدة،
those of us who don't want to adapt can write the way we're used to writing,
والذين لايريدون التكيف منا يستطيعون الكتابة كما اعتدنا،
and hopefully, time will cement the new rules in place.
على أمل أن الوقت سيثبت القواعد الجديدة.
The success of every spelling reform that affects deeply rooted habits
نجاح كل إصلاح إملائي الذي يؤثر في العادات المتأصلة جذرياً
lies in caution, agreement, gradualism and tolerance.
يقع في الحذر والتوافق والتدرج والتسامح.
At the same time, can't allow the attachment to old customs
في الوقت نفسه، لانسمح للتعلق بالعادات القديمة
impede us from moving forward.
أن يعيقنا عن المضي قدماً.
The best tribute we can pay to the past
أفضل تكريم يمكن أن نقدمه للماضي
is to improve upon what it's given us.
هو التحسين فيما قد قدمه لنا.
So I believe that we must reach an agreement,
لذلك أعتقد أنه علينا أن نصل لاتفاق،
that academies must reach an agreement,
أن تصل الأكاديميات لاتفاق،
and purge from our spelling rules
وتطهر من قواعد إملاؤنا
all the habits we practice just for the sake of tradition,
كل العادات التي نمارسها لمجرد أنها عرف،
even if they are useless now.
حتى لو كانت لا تجدي نفعاً.
I'm convinced that if we do that
لدي قناعة أننا لو فعلنا ذلك
in the humble but extremely important realm of language,
في المجال اللغوي المتواضع لكن ذي أهمية عظمى،
we'll be leaving a better future to the next generations.
سوف نترك مستقبل أفضل للأجيال القادمة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)